<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>random on The Writer At Heart</title><link>https://japananh.github.io/tags/random/</link><description>Recent content in random on The Writer At Heart</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2022 00:38:47 +0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://japananh.github.io/tags/random/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Autumn Notes - A Reconsideration of The Real Life</title><link>https://japananh.github.io/p/autumn-notes-a-reconsideration-of-real-life/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2022 00:38:47 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://japananh.github.io/p/autumn-notes-a-reconsideration-of-real-life/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://japananh.github.io/p/autumn-notes-a-reconsideration-of-real-life/cover.jpeg" alt="Featured image of post Autumn Notes - A Reconsideration of The Real Life" />&lt;p>&lt;strong>Autumn Notes&lt;/strong> is the last note of the series 100 Days of Challenge that I wrote in the Autumn of 2022. This is a random-thought post as usual. The content is about what I learned, how I overcome my difficulties, and why things work.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="dopamine">Dopamine&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Loss of motivation is the most difficult thing that I need to deal with in the recent year. Working on others’ projects, fixing bugs, following others’ rules, and sometimes dealing with toxic work culture drove me crazy and exhausted. I found myself lost and overwhelmed by almost everything.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At that time, my English got better and I started to listen to &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.youtube.com/c/AndrewHubermanLab" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>The Huberman Lab&lt;/a> at their very first episodes. The &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=p3JLaF_4Tz8" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>conversation&lt;/a> between Prof. Huberman (the host) and Dr. Anna Lembke (the guest) about Dopamine enlighten me about why and how all these things happened. I didn&amp;rsquo;t notice that my dopamine level was very low at that time so I have no mood on anything.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Dopamine&lt;/strong> is &lt;strong>a feel-good neurotransmitter&lt;/strong> that plays a role in many functions in the body, including motivation, mood, attention, and memory. If your dopamine level is very low, you might have almost no motivation to do anything.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A &lt;strong>neurotransmitter&lt;/strong> is a chemical messenger that transmits signals in the body. It also acts as a hormone.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>To learn more about Dopamine and how it works to control your mood, I recommend you read the amazing and detailed Dopamine paper: &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4826767/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4826767/&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After a year of trial and error, here are 3 things that significant improve my mood:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Viewing sunlight in the morning (before 8 AM) and/or in the late afternoon (after 4 PM).&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>I think the lack of vitamin D (D3) is due to covering my body by wearing like a ninja outside and working indoors all day. In the summer, it seemed reasonable when I protected my body this way. But in the winter, the lack of sunlight decreased my performance at work. I felt tired and low mood all day.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>No one ever told me about the relationship between sunlight (especially blue light) and the alert system in the human brain. Sunlight suspends melatonin in the human brain. Melatonin is a hormone that your brain produces in response to darkness. That way if we feel alert when we view the sunlight.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For more information, I hightly recommend you watch this episode from The Huberman Lab: &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UF0nqolsNZc" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UF0nqolsNZc&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol start="2">
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Magnesium&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Magnesium plays many crucial roles in the body, such as supporting muscle and nerve function and energy production. Huberman mentioned &lt;strong>Magnesium&lt;/strong> as a great supplement for sleep, mood, and exercising in one episode (sorry, I forgot its name). You can read more studies about the benefits of Magnesium in &lt;a class="link" href="https://examine.com/summaries/?filter=supplements&amp;amp;value=magnesium" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Examine&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I started to use Magnesium supplements 5 months ago. My dose is &lt;strong>400 mg a day&lt;/strong> (an average dose for women my age), &lt;strong>before bed&lt;/strong>. You can use it after your workout session or before bed depending on the way you feel better. I was dealing with sleep quality so I used it before bed. If your priority is improving training, you can use it after training.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol start="3">
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Sleep control&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>I tracked my sleep quality with a smart band that connected to my phone via Bluetooth. The app analyzed my sleep via some indicators such as the time woke up, the time to bed, regularity of rising time, deep sleep continuity, etc. When all indicators are normal, it means high sleep quality. Trying to improve as many indicators as I can help me feel relaxed and calm the next day.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-rules-of-thirds">The rules of thirds&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I started my powerlifting journey and prepared for my first meet 4 months ago. This sport is not easy for me, an absolute beginner. I was struggling with SBD techniques for the first 2 months (didn&amp;rsquo;t know how to hold the bar and arching in bench, good-morning squat, conven-sumo deadlift, etc). I cried, yelled at myself and thought of quitting it. The rules of thirds by &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.instagram.com/alexipappas" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Alexi Pappas&lt;/a>, came into my life as a magic Mantra.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I couldn&amp;rsquo;t hit my last exercise 2 weeks ago. Then it happened again a week later. 2 weeks left before the meet. I was crying so hard. I didn&amp;rsquo;t know why. My mood was down. Then I thought of the rules of thirds and counted my sessions. 2 crappy days (3.3%) along the 4 months (60 sessions). The ratio is quite good. Well, the number never lies you. No cry, no anxiety.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;When you are chasing a dream or doing anything hard, you&amp;rsquo;ve meant to feel &lt;strong>GOOD&lt;/strong> a third of the time, &lt;strong>OKAY&lt;/strong> a third of the time, and &lt;strong>CRAPPY&lt;/strong> a third of the time. If the ratio roughly in that range, then you&amp;rsquo;re doing fine. Today was a crappy day, along your dream chasing.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Note: Alexi Pappas is a Greek-American runner, filmmaker, actor, and writer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Reference: &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.instagram.com/tv/CgF3hJWlqdM" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>https://www.instagram.com/tv/CgF3hJWlqdM&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sleepiness">Sleepiness&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Beside the loss of motivation, I also deal with the sleepiness in the morning that affected my performance at work.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>First, I started with nutrition as the easiest way to manipulate my sleep. I used to be a high-carbs eater (&amp;gt;= 60%) for a long time. It turned out &lt;strong>reducing carbs down to 50%&lt;/strong> helps reduce sleepiness because my stomach doesn’t need to spend a lot of energy to digest carbs and the insulin level won’t peak too high.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Intermittent fasting&lt;/strong> also works well for me, I skip breakfast on the day I do work out in the morning due to no time to cook in the morning. I maintained macros, just no breakfast. After 3 months, I saw some amazing results such as:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>My body recomposition improved, my abs decreased from 71 to 68 cm.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I look leaner and don’t be annoyed because of my full stomach. I started to realize that I love an empty stomach in the morning.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>No sleepiness in the morning and afternoon, except my sleeping period, is too short (below 5 hours) or the sleeping quality is not good.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>As a result, the incredible thing happened that I started to feel hungry at meal time (3 times a day in the morning/noon/night) after a year of no hungry at all. Therefore, I stopped intermittent fasting and my eating routine back to normal. Life always compensate us in some way if we work hard.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Second, I still fall asleep more quickly on rainy/cloudy days. The greatest way to find a solution of any problem is figuring out why it happened. Here are some reasons that cause sleepiness on rainy/cloudy days.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The increased negative ion content in the air.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Rainy sounds are lullabies.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Studies have found that when rain sounds enter people’s brains, the brain unconsciously relaxes and produces alpha waves, which are very close to the state of the brain when a human sleeps.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Increased secretion of melatonin in the body when it darks
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.sleepfoundation.org/melatonin" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Darkness prompts the pineal gland to start producing melatonin while light causes that production to stop.&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Decreased oxygen content in the air.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Oxygen can stimulate the brain and make us feel refreshed. When it rains, there is more water vapor in the air, which results in lower air pressure and a relative decrease in oxygen content. In such a situation, the brain begins to slack off, and people will feel sleepy.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>When understood the causes, I didn&amp;rsquo;t found myself lost in negative thoughts that ruined my days. I came up with some solutions.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Make the room as bright as possible (Light suspends the melatonin).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Take a deep breath (To increase the oxygen content in my body).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Increase heart rate by exercising or talking to someone (Increases my dopamine level and alert my brain).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="compassion">Compassion&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="link" href="https://lexfridman.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Lex Fridman&lt;/a>, the famous AI researcher, is the first guy to teach me about &lt;strong>compassion&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>love&lt;/strong> on his podcast, but Q is the guy who motivated me to make my first move. I&amp;rsquo;m quite good at Maths and logic but very bad at learning abstract things and emotions. Compassion requires deep observation, mindfulness, and patience.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Self-help books taught me to spend most of my time with great people.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;We are the average of the five people we spend the most time with.&amp;rdquo; - &lt;a class="link" href="jimrohn.com" >Jim Rohn&lt;/a> said.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Great&amp;rdquo; means wealthy, flourishing career, good-looking, blissful relationship, etc. If you don&amp;rsquo;t fall under the criteria, I will ignore you. That mindset caused me a ton of trouble in daily life. I compared myself to others and developed low self-esteem. I also treated people unfairly by their &amp;ldquo;success status&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>How do I know where I am in my success status when I don&amp;rsquo;t compare myself to others?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When I thought I&amp;rsquo;m on a higher level, I ignored the existence of the &amp;ldquo;lower&amp;rdquo; people. On the other side, I felt &amp;ldquo;motivated&amp;rdquo; to move forward when I see success people. But that motivation was just an illusion. It took me weeks, months, or even years to accomplish my goals. Meanwhile, most time I felt jealous and ashamed by the thought I was not good enough, or people might call it &lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;Imposter syndrome&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When Q told me about the class hierarchy of wealthy people vs poor people, we debated for an hour and I suspected most of his arguments and reasoning. We didn&amp;rsquo;t discuss more about this topic after that. A few weeks later, I saw a comic named &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/thewokesalaryman/posts/pfbid02MoANmdVSANzPG3TGmmEapui67LQAtpTXMixzD3DWWWZk8FaoT9rqpLZNQFK6KAZTl" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Hedonic treadmill&lt;/a> about the way we live our lives by breaking old boxes and fall into more comfortable boxes, do it again until we are satisfied with our lives. I found my Aha! moment.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When I was in a fresher position, I thought of my career path and saw my coworkers and my friends working so hard to get their dream jobs. They double/triple their salary in the next 2 years and became superman at work. When I compared myself to them, I was distressed. I didn&amp;rsquo;t realize that they have NO personal life. They work all day and hang out with family or friends at weekends or holidays. They don&amp;rsquo;t exercise and don&amp;rsquo;t have a &amp;ldquo;balance work-life&amp;rdquo;. Their body shapes and their health become worse. Some of them fall into the mindset of cold-hearted as I did. I respect their hard-working, and they contribute value to the world but I quite dislike the way they live.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The way I disliked my family is they were born in a box and lived their whole life in that box. No ambition, no improvement. I blamed them for laziness and backwardness. I felt ashamed of my behaviors. They have their choices. They are satisfied with their boxes. So do I.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This is the last note of the series &lt;a class="link" href="http://thewriteratheart.com/categories/100-days-of-challenge/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>&lt;strong>100 Days of Challenge&lt;/strong>&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I started this series just want to write down what I observed in my daily life with the philosophy is &lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;Doing it for fun&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>. A year look back, I have a blog with 100 posts and some new friends came into my life unexpectedly. I realize that I love &lt;strong>reading&lt;/strong>, &lt;strong>writing&lt;/strong>, and &lt;strong>sharing&lt;/strong>. The more I write, the more I understand myself and become a better me. Smart brain with a compassionate heart.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Welcome to my world!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Random people make my day</title><link>https://japananh.github.io/p/random-people-make-my-day/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Jul 2022 23:09:51 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://japananh.github.io/p/random-people-make-my-day/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://japananh.github.io/p/random-people-make-my-day/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Random people make my day" />&lt;h2 id="the-blind-pianist">The blind pianist&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I attended a piano concert this week. The blind girl played a piece by Chopin that was named &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9E6b3swbnWg" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Nocturne op .9 No. 2&lt;/a>. The melody was so familiar to me that I guessed its name correctly. I wept tears of joy to see her smile and her performance. Although, she made a few mistakes and her face looked worried a bit but for me, she did a great job. When her dark brighten me, I knew hope never ends.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="ben-hoyt">Ben Hoyt&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This guy created an &lt;a class="link" href="https://github.com/benhoyt/goawk" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>AWK interpreter that is written in the Go language&lt;/a>. He was inspired by the book &lt;a class="link" href="https://ia903404.us.archive.org/0/items/pdfy-MgN0H1joIoDVoIC7/The_AWK_Programming_Language.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>AWK programming&lt;/a> and his father who taught him coding when he was a kid. I was just wondering if I would make the same story when my kid wrote in his/her blog &amp;ldquo;My mom taught me science and programming when I was a kid. She was my inspiration to create XYZ library&amp;rdquo;. For more info about his work, you can check out his blog &lt;a class="link" href="https://benhoyt.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Besides his successful career, he also has an amazing life with piano and a fantastic family with his wife and 3 lovely daughters. I enjoy reading their family blog named &lt;a class="link" href="https://aliensintheapple.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Alien in the Apple&lt;/a>. I hope I would become a great mother someday.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-classical-music-lover">The classical music lover&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I met T, an introverted technical man with a heart for classical music, in the small tech talk about JavaScript that I was a host in 2019 in Hanoi. We exchanged Facebook contact but didn&amp;rsquo;t talk for a long time. I was a shy girl so I read all of his posts and loved them so much but never texted him. He has been practicing guitar for over 10 years. This year, he decided to learn violin. I wanna try to learn the violin to make sure I love it as much as the feeling when I enjoy the violin expert playing pieces of classical music. So I asked him to try his violin. It turned out, that I did love it. We also had a great conversation about violin, physics, and religion.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We met again in the Vietnam Museum of Ethnology this week. When he told me about the journey of a woman who bought land in Dalat to live her self-sufficient lifestyle and then realized that her dream was impractical, some pieces of my memories came back. I had a question that I tried to answer for many years since I graduated from high school.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Why did I turn boring quickly and NOT wanna see people?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Why did I NOT have any interested in any conversation with anyone for many years?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>All of his stories were so cute and hilarious with his passion for art and science. &lt;em>He was exactly the type of friend that I usually hung out with when I was in school.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Most people grow up and lost their ability to be freedom of mind because of their social responsibilities and their willingness. All the conversations I had with them were about career growth, financial advice, or general topics such as weather, food, traveling, etc. Nothing touched my heart. I felt empty and exhausted after that but didn&amp;rsquo;t know why. We smiled. The place was comfortable. I knew there was something wrong but I didn&amp;rsquo;t know what is it. Today was the best day of my life. I found it. FANTASTIC!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>How to grow glutes</title><link>https://japananh.github.io/p/how-to-grow-glutes/</link><pubDate>Sun, 27 Feb 2022 21:44:27 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://japananh.github.io/p/how-to-grow-glutes/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://japananh.github.io/p/how-to-grow-glutes/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post How to grow glutes" />&lt;h2 id="the-rule-of-thirds">The rule of thirds&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The rules of thirds are developed by &lt;strong>Bret Contreras&lt;/strong> (aka &lt;strong>The glutes guy&lt;/strong>). He is the &lt;strong>inventor of Hip Thrust&lt;/strong> and a world-leading glute expert.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.hashnode.com/res/hashnode/image/upload/v1645959549731/o7mnYz_ev.png"
loading="lazy"
alt="rule-of-third.png"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To maximize the potential of the glutes, the rules of thirds said that&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>In terms of effort, around 1/3 of your sets should be carried out to failure or 1 rep shy of failure, 1/3 of your sets should be performed to 2-3 reps shy of failure, and 1/3 of your sets should be taken nowhere close to failure.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Source: &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BfzRPC2AS_r/?utm_source=ig_embed" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>https://www.instagram.com/p/BfzRPC2AS_r/?utm_source=ig_embed&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="exercise-categories">Exercise categories&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.hashnode.com/res/hashnode/image/upload/v1645959598661/tQpfnyWzB.jpg"
loading="lazy"
alt="90e6df974fbcbf82053572b091b702b4.jpg"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Vertically loaded exercises&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Horizontally loaded exercises&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Lateral/Rotary loaded exercises&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>- Squat &amp;amp; squat variation&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- Deadlift &amp;amp; deadlift variation&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- Leg press&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- Step-ups&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- Lunges&lt;/td>
&lt;td>- Hip thrust and hip thrust variation&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- Bridges&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- Frog pump&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- Back extension&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- Reverse hypers&lt;/td>
&lt;td>- Sidekick exercises&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- Kickback exercises&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- Hip abduction exercises&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- Fire hydrant&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- Lateral band walk&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- Swings&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>- Develop lower glutes&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- Low reps: 3 - 10 reps&lt;/td>
&lt;td>- Develop upper/lower glutes&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- Medium reps: &amp;gt;= 10&lt;/td>
&lt;td>- Develop upper glutes&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- High reps: &amp;gt;= 15 to AMAP (as much as possible)&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Vertically loaded glute exercises are the hardest on the body and work lower than upper glute max fibers.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Horizontal is less taxing overall but highly activates both the upper and lower subdivisions.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Frontal plane lateral exercises completely target the upper subdivision of the glute max, whereas transverse plane hip abduction and hip external rotation exercises work both the upper and lower fibers.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>To make things more complicated, you also have blends and combinations of vectors.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Glute dominant exercises&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Quad dominant exercises&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Hamstring dominant exercises&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>- Hip thrust and hip thrust variation&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> - Bridges&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- Frog pump&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- Sidekick exercises&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- Kickback exercises&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- Hip abduction exercises&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- Fire hydrant&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- Lateral band walk&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- RKC plank&lt;/td>
&lt;td>- Squat &amp;amp; squat variation&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- Step-ups&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- Leg press&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- Sled pushes&lt;/td>
&lt;td>- Deadlift &amp;amp; deadlift variation&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- Back extension&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- Reverse hypers&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- Swings&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- Knee flexion exercises&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>- &lt;em>Hip thrust&lt;/em> should be placed at the beginning of your workouts.&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- &lt;em>Hip abduction exercises&lt;/em> are great for burnouts and developing upper glutes. They should be placed at the end of your workouts.&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- &lt;em>RKC plank&lt;/em> is great to work the core and should be the last exercise.&lt;/td>
&lt;td>- &lt;em>Squats&lt;/em> should be placed at the beginning of your workouts.&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- &lt;em>Step-ups&lt;/em>, &lt;em>Leg press&lt;/em> should be placed in the middle of your workouts.&lt;/td>
&lt;td>- &lt;em>Deadlift&lt;/em> should be placed at the beginning of your workouts.&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->- &lt;em>Back extension&lt;/em> and &lt;em>Reverse hyper exercises&lt;/em> elicit higher glutes activation than other hamstring-dominant exercises.&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;h2 id="qa">Q&amp;amp;A&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The glute guy said 3 to 5 depending on the volume. I often train my glutes with heavyweights (around 70 - 80% of 1RM - 1 Rep Max). I can only train my glutes 3 days a week. My lower body will be sore. I need 1 - 2 days to recover. But if you use the medium to lightweights, you can train up to 5 times a week.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Low reps: 3 to 5&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Medium: 8 to 10&lt;/li>
&lt;li>High reps: &amp;gt; 10&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>There are no exercises that work for everybody. Everyone is different. I saw a lot of girls with great glutes doing mostly medium/high reps schema. I love low/medium reps schema but I try to keep everything in balance.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I always start with the low reps exercises: vertically exercises such as Squat or Deadlift or Hip thrust, followed by the medium reps exercises such as squat variation exercises (Split squats, Bulgarian split squats, Step-ups, …) or deadlift variation exercises (single-leg deadlift, back extension, sumo deadlift, …) and finish with the lateral/rotary exercises (15 to AMAP) such as Seated Hip Abduction, Sidekick, Kickback, …&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If your form is not good, please find a mentor, or at least try to firm yourself when you&amp;rsquo;re working out, then compare your form with the correct way that was taught in the book &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.amazon.com/Starting-Strength-Mark-Rippetoe-ebook-dp-B006XJR5ZA/dp/B006XJR5ZA/ref=mt_other?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;me=&amp;amp;qid=" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Starting strengh&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It is not easy for a novice to pick the proper weights for each exercise. If you don&amp;rsquo;t have a mentor. Here is the formula that I use to pick up my weight.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For example, if you want to do 10 reps of Squats, you should pick a weight that you can do a maximum of 10-12 reps.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sample-templates">Sample templates&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This is an example of my one-week workout. My workouts change every month depending on my current physique, my mood, my routines, and my goals.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Monday (reps x sets)&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Wednesday (reps x sets)&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Friday (reps x sets)&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>1. Barbell back squat 5x4&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->2. Hip thrust 10x3&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->3. Standing pull through 15x3&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->4. Cable sidekick 15/legx4&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1. Conventional Deadlift 5x4&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->2. Split squat 10/legx3&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->3. Frog Pump 15x3&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->4. Seated hip abduction 20x4&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1. Barbell back squat 5x4&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->2. Stiff-deadlift 10x3&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->3. Cable sidekick 15/legx4&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->4. Fire hydrant 20/legx4&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Monday (reps x sets)&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Wednesday (reps x sets)&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Friday (reps x sets)&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>1. Barbell hip thrust 10x4&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->2. Chin-ups 5x4&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->3. Barbell back squats 10x4&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->4. Lat Pulldown 10x4&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->5. Swings 20*4&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->6. Cable sidekick 15/legx4&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->7. RKC Plank 30sx1&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1. Barbell hip thrust 10x4&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->2. Overhead Press 10x4&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->3. Split squat 10/legx4&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->4. Push-ups 5x4&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->5. Frog Pump 10x4&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->6. Seated hip abduction 20x4&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->7. Landmine 10x1&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1. Conventional Deadlift 5x4&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->2. Dumbell shoulder press 10x4&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->3. Barbell hip thrust 10x4&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->4. Chess press 10x4&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->5. Banded hip thrust 20x4&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->6. Fire hydrant 20/legx4&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->7. Hanging leg raise 15x1&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>You can try sample glute workouts from Bret (aka The Glute Guy - the Hip thrust inventor) &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.instagram.com/p/B3sPLrtA3LL/?igshid=qmlsfjfecddn&amp;amp;epik=dj0yJnU9ZGh1N2hOdmF1QjRrSk5jVWhDSlFfdWUzelNHRTc0ZnAmcD0wJm49LVVpVTVhVmlkX00yUEtZN05NdUp3USZ0PUFBQUFBR0JQWk44" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="references">References&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BfzRPC2AS_r/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;amp;ig_rid=7954bb41-c212-4d37-8df7-28679e1fc9e9" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Glute training vectors&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.instagram.com/p/Be-atfPg_Ke/?utm_source=ig_embed" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>The rule of thirds&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UKNqDd_epnI" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UKNqDd_epnI&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>How does Google search work?</title><link>https://japananh.github.io/p/how-does-google-search-work/</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2022 06:42:53 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://japananh.github.io/p/how-does-google-search-work/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://japananh.github.io/p/how-does-google-search-work/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post How does Google search work?" />&lt;p>How does the Google search engine goes through the over 30 trillion web pages on the internet and find the top 10 results in just half a second, on average?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Google doesn&amp;rsquo;t actually visit every page on the internet every time you ask it something. Google stores information about web pages in databases (table of information, like in Excel), and it uses algorithms that read those databases to decide what to show you.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="crawl-all-web-pages">Crawl all web pages&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Google&amp;rsquo;s algorithms build a database of every webpage on the internet. Google uses programs called spiders to &amp;ldquo;crawl&amp;rdquo; over web pages until it finds all of them. The spiders start on a few web pages and add those to Google&amp;rsquo;s list of pages, called &amp;ldquo;index&amp;rdquo;. Then, the spiders follow all the outgoing links on those pages and find a new set of pages, which they add to the index. Next, they follow all the links on those pages, and so on, until Google can&amp;rsquo;t find anything else.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="word-search">Word search&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>If you search Google, it grabs your query (the text you typed into the search bar) and looks through its index to find the web pages that are most relevant.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Google uses keyword density to show the most frequently used words on the current page, then find the page that had the most matches.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="page-rank">Page rank&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>PageRank (PR) is an algorithm used by Google Search to rank web pages in their search engine results. It is named after both the term &amp;ldquo;web page&amp;rdquo; and co-founder Larry Page. According to Google:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>PageRank works by counting the number and quality of links to a page to determine a rough estimate of how important the website is. The underlying assumption is that more important websites are likely to receive more links from other websites.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>For instance, at a party, you know someone is popular when they&amp;rsquo;re surrounded by other popular people. PageRank gives each web page a score that&amp;rsquo;s based on the PageRank scores of every other page that links to that page.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="seo">SEO&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>SEO (Search engine optimization) is the process of improving the quality and quantity of website traffic to a website or a web page from search engines. The most basic form of SEO is getting more pages linked to your page. SEO also includes plenty more techniques, such as putting the right keywords in your page&amp;rsquo;s title and headings or making all of your site&amp;rsquo;s pages link to each other.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="references">References&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a class="link" href="" >Swipe to unlock&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>I'm feeling so bad</title><link>https://japananh.github.io/p/i-m-feeling-so-bad/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Jan 2022 04:36:17 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://japananh.github.io/p/i-m-feeling-so-bad/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://japananh.github.io/p/i-m-feeling-so-bad/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post I'm feeling so bad" />&lt;p>Tôi nghĩ rằng sẽ có rất nhiều lân trong đời bạn sẽ thốt lên câu &amp;ldquo;Tôi thấy thật tệ&amp;rdquo; (I&amp;rsquo;m feeling so bad). Tệ thường được gán cho cái mác &amp;ldquo;yếu đuối&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;kém cỏi&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;hèn&amp;rdquo;. Điều này là không đúng. Hầu hết cảm giác tệ tới từ sự bất ổn kéo dài trong cuộc sống làm cạn kiệt dopamine và nó là tín hiệu cho thấy bạn cần thay đổi.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Não bộ không phân biệt được trải nghiệm thật hay giả về mặt cảm xúc. Chừng nào hình ảnh tiêu cực còn chạy vòng vòng trong đầu thì chừng đó thời gian bạn sẽ bị nó nuốt chửng. Lúc này, bạn cần kiếm một việc thật dễ, vui vẻ, lành mạnh, thực hiện nó để cho não bạn được nhảy số sang chủ đề khác.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Bước một&lt;/strong>, nếu bạn thích xem phim. Điều này chứng tỏ dopamine tăng nhanh khi bạn xem phim. Bạn nên có sẵn 1 list các danh sách các phim có nội dung vui vẻ, hài hước, tránh những phim nhiều cảm xúc tiêu cực. Vì trong lúc rối bời có thể bạn sẽ chọn nhầm một phim có nội dung tệ và nguy cơ thất vọng (tụt dopamine) cao.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Bước hai&lt;/strong>, sau khi bình tĩnh hơn, nhờ nạp dopamine từ việc xem phim, bạn nên ngồi xuống và trả lời những câu hỏi sau.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Điều gì đã khiến tôi cảm thấy tệ?&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Chuyện này bắt đầu từ khi nào? Giọt nước nào đầu tiên rơi vào cái cốc?&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Tôi làm gì để cải thiện tình hình bây giờ?&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Làm sao để tôi ngăn điều này xảy ra vào lần tới?&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Trả lời càng kỹ bao nhiêu thì lần sau khả năng tái lỗi của bạn sẽ thấp hơn hẳn. Với tôi, khi tôi đã phải dùng tới phim để tăng mood thì đấy là lúc tôi thấy TỆ NHẤT. Bạn có thể sẽ có câu trả lời khác với tôi.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Bước ba&lt;/strong>, thực hiện những gì bạn đã viết trong &lt;strong>tối thiểu 21 ngày liên tục&lt;/strong> để chúng trở thành thói quen, tự động đi vào tiềm thức. Thiếu bước này, những thứ bạn viết ra ở bước hai sẽ trở nên vô ích. Một số người xây dựng thói quen lâu hơn người khác và việc này có thể lên tới &lt;em>vài tháng cho tới ba năm&lt;/em>. Nếu bạn miss vài ngày, không sao cả. Bạn không phải là siêu nhân.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Chúng ta thường nghĩ là năng lượng tiêu cực tới từ những người xung quanh. Nếu bạn nghĩ đồng nghiệp lười biếng khiến bạn lười biếng theo, bạn có thể thử đổi môi trường. Biết đâu bạn đúng. Nhưng hãy cẩn thận với chính mình.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Who has been an influence on you?</title><link>https://japananh.github.io/p/who-has-been-an-influence-on-you/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Jan 2022 00:27:52 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://japananh.github.io/p/who-has-been-an-influence-on-you/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://japananh.github.io/p/who-has-been-an-influence-on-you/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Who has been an influence on you?" />&lt;p>We all have people who have changed our lives. People can change your life in a positive or negative way. Master Thich Nhat Hanh is my inspiration to live a better life.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>His drama talks and his mantras help me overcome my anger. I read this mantra many many times years ago until the anger was gone. If you&amp;rsquo;re dealing with your anger, I hope this helps.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="link" href="https://langmai.org/cong-tam-quan/thong-bach/cao-pho-thien-su-thich-nhat-hanh-vien-tich/?fbclid=IwAR23iBZz9j5DBOESkZd0UV6hI_f1V3m0VfyGptOTKQRRX-Ctx8EdU-7qPDQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>He left our beautiful world today&lt;/a>. His compassion and his wisdom are still our guides and shell never pass away. &amp;ldquo;I place my faith in Amida Buddha.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="anger-mantra">Anger Mantra&lt;/h2>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;div class="chroma">
&lt;table class="lntable">&lt;tr>&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code>&lt;span class="lnt"> 1
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 2
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 3
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 4
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 5
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 6
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 7
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 8
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 9
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">10
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">11
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">12
&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>
&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-md" data-lang="md">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">Breathing in,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">I know that anger is here.
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">Breathing out,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">I know that the anger is not me.
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">Breathing in,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">I know that anger is unpleasant.
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">Breathing out,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">I know this feeling will pass.
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">Breathing in,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">I am calm.
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">Breathing out,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">I am strong enough to take care of this anger.
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>&lt;/tr>&lt;/table>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.hashnode.com/res/hashnode/image/upload/v1642869848861/VkrI6wsYF.jpeg"
loading="lazy"
alt="49b6caa5e5704c24aa7aa502164fd9f3.jpg"
>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>How to create a better morning routine?</title><link>https://japananh.github.io/p/how-to-create-a-better-morning-routine/</link><pubDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 23:25:34 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://japananh.github.io/p/how-to-create-a-better-morning-routine/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://japananh.github.io/p/how-to-create-a-better-morning-routine/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post How to create a better morning routine?" />&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m a morning person. My most productive time is in the morning, so I try to accomplish as many things as I can before lunch. It took me a while to find my morning routine with trials and errors. Today, I&amp;rsquo;m gonna share with you my morning routines.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="making-your-bed">Making your bed&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This is the first thing you should do. I got this advice from Tim Ferriss on his channel on Youtube. You can check it out &lt;a class="link" href="https://youtu.be/LHAyE0UC5I4?t=50" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>here&lt;/a>. He explained that&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Accomplishing one thing at the beginning of the day no matter what happens with unforeseen variables for the rest of day.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>You will return to a made bed at the end of the day. As a bookmark beginning an end, it sets you up psychologically to be more productive.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>If you work at home, an external mess creates an internal mess.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="awake-nervous-system">Awake nervous system&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The next thing you should do is that awake your nervous system.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I got this advice from Huberman (an American neuroscientist) in his article. Blue light from sunlight early in the morning can block &lt;strong>melatonin&lt;/strong>, a hormone made in the body to regulate night and day cycles or sleep-wake cycles. It is similar to an alarm that wakes you up in the morning and makes you sleepy in the evening.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If seeing the blue light is not enough for you, light exercises such as push-ups, pull-ups, or a few minutes of cardio will help. It can increase your heartbeat, increase your blood oxygen level, and put you in an alert state.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="stay-focused">Stay focused&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Sometimes, you feel alert in the morning but your mind is wandering so you cannot focus on anything. These tips below bring my mind back, so I hope it works for you.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tim Ferriss introduced me to this technique. You can read anything that excites you. Just wrap a book or a magazine. This technique is effective because it traps your monkey mind on paper so you can get on with your day. I often look at my daily plan and read it out loud.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>By starting a meditation practice and tuning into your breath and body when you first wake up, you become more aware of your thoughts–and that monkey mind. Some thoughts might make sense while other thoughts seem to come out of nowhere. Especially, when you&amp;rsquo;re wake up after a nightmare.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="breakfast">Breakfast&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Some people avoid sugar and think it makes them fat. That&amp;rsquo;s a myth. A little sugar (below 3 grams) is just fine. If your brain doesn&amp;rsquo;t have enough &amp;ldquo;sugar&amp;rdquo;, you will start to crave sweet foods. By saying &amp;ldquo;sugar&amp;rdquo;, I mean you should provide enough energy for your brain in the morning. Energy can come from a lot of sources. I highly recommend people to have &lt;em>whole foods with high carbs or high proteins or a mix with both of them&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="keep-your-mouth-clean">Keep your mouth clean&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Some people are very busy or lazy so they don&amp;rsquo;t even put a few minutes to clean their mouths. Early meetings make people feel annoyed because of bad breath. Keeping your mouth clean is not only a personal norm but a &lt;strong>SOCIAL&lt;/strong> norm.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>An &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.healthline.com/health/should-you-brush-your-teeth-before-or-after-breakfast#:~:text=Waiting%2030%20minutes%20to%20an,especially%20after%20having%20acidic%20foods." target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>article&lt;/a> in healthlin.com show that&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Waiting 30 minutes to an hour after eating to brush your teeth is the best way to ensure that you&amp;rsquo;re protecting your teeth and not tampering with your enamel. The American Dental Association recommends you wait 60 minutes after eating before you brush, especially after having acidic foods.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></description></item><item><title>Don't ask to ask, just ask</title><link>https://japananh.github.io/p/don-t-ask-to-ask-just-ask/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Jan 2022 18:43:04 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://japananh.github.io/p/don-t-ask-to-ask-just-ask/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://japananh.github.io/p/don-t-ask-to-ask-just-ask/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Don't ask to ask, just ask" />&lt;h2 id="case-1">Case 1&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In forums or groups on social media, I saw some people pop in and say something like that.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Any JavaScript experts around?&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>This is a bad form, for several reasons. What the person is actually asking here is&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Any JavaScript experts around who are willing to commit to my problem, whatever that might turn out to be, even if it&amp;rsquo;s not actually related to JavaScript could answer my question?&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>There are plenty of reasons why people DO have the knowledge would NOT admit to it. The unclear question proves your laziness. Why people should do the work to solve your problem if you&amp;rsquo;re not willing to do it?&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="case-2">Case 2&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Some people send me a message then stop there until I reply.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Hey, I have a question.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>or&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Alo, I have a bug.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>They only describe their problems until I ask them to clarify them.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Hi, what&amp;rsquo;s wrong?&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>This is also a bad form. Why not jump into your problem so I don&amp;rsquo;t need to ask an extra question.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Hey, I&amp;rsquo;m reading [book] and I&amp;rsquo;m confused with the [concept]. Could you have time to explain it to me?&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>or&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Alo. I do [problem] with JavaScript and [other relevant info]. I tried [what you did] but it didn&amp;rsquo;t work. Could you help me out?&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The point here is &lt;strong>not to ask, just ask&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Day 50</title><link>https://japananh.github.io/p/day-50/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Jan 2022 00:46:52 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://japananh.github.io/p/day-50/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://japananh.github.io/p/day-50/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Day 50" />&lt;p>Chào mọi người, vèo cái đã tới ngày 50. Vậy là tôi đã đi được một nửa quãng đường rồi.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Mọi người có gợi ý gì cho thử thách sắp tới thì comment vào bài nhé.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Trong bài này, tôi sẽ trích ra một vài ghi chú từ cuốn &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/23719305-how-emotions-are-made" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>How emotions are made&lt;/a> của &lt;a class="link" href="https://lisafeldmanbarrett.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Lisa Feldman Barrett&lt;/a>. Đây là cuốn sách đầu tiên của năm 2022.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tôi đọc cuốn này vì muốn hiểu hơn về cảm xúc. Tôi nghĩ lời khuyên &lt;em>Gác cảm xúc sang một bên&lt;/em> tới từ sự thiếu hiểu biết hơn là từ sự thấu hiểu. Đây là ví dụ điển hình của xu hướng &lt;em>né tránh những thứ mà bản thân chưa rõ và che đậy nó bằng từ ngữ hoa mỹ&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-theory-of-constructed-emotions-vs-the-classical-view">The theory of constructed emotions vs The classical view&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Tác giả phát triển một lý thuyết kiến tạo xã hội (a social constructionist theory)
tên là &lt;strong>Lý thuyết về cảm xúc được xây dựng&lt;/strong> - &lt;a class="link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theory_of_constructed_emotion" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>The theory of constructed emotions&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Lý thuyết về cảm xúc được xây dựng nói rằng não của bạn tạo nên mọi thứ bạn trải nghiệm, bao gồm cả cảm xúc của bạn.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Your brain invisibly constructs everything you experience, including emotions.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The classical view: Sự kiện bên ngoài thế giới kích hoạt cảm xúc của chúng ta.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The classical view is intuitive - events in the world trigger emotional reactions inside of us.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="the-myth-of-universal-emotions">The myth of universal emotions&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Một trong những luận điểm nêu ra ở The classical view là nhận dạng cảm xúc là phổ biến (universal).&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Emotion recognition is universal.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Tức là giả sử bạn cho một người Mỹ và một người Việt Nam hay một ai đó từ những nền văn hóa khác nhìn vào bức ảnh có hình một cô gái vẻ mặt &amp;ldquo;buồn&amp;rdquo; thì họ cùng phải nhận thức được rằng là người trong ảnh đang &amp;ldquo;buồn&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tuy nhiên, khi thực hiện những thử nghiệm với những nhóm người từ nhiều nền văn hóa khác nhau thì nhóm của Lisa lại nhận thấy tỷ lệ trả lời đúng là 58%, rất thấp. Một vài cảm xúc dễ bị nhầm lẫn với nhau khi chỉ nhìn vào khuôn mặt như sợ hãi, ngạc nhiên, tức giận.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Họ kết luận rằng nhận dạng cảm xúc phụ thuộc vào cả ngữ cảnh (context) và nhiều yếu tố phức tạp khác chứ không hề &amp;ldquo;universal&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="emotion-concepts">Emotion concepts&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Não bạn liên tục tạo ra khái niệm cảm xúc (emotion concepts). Khi nhắc tới &amp;ldquo;buồn rầu&amp;rdquo;, các nerouns của bạn sẽ lục tìm những ký ức phù hợp với từ &amp;ldquo;buồn&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Đối với một đứa trẻ mới sinh (infant), chưa hề có các khái niệm cảm xúc. Việc hình thành các khái niệm của bé tới từ việc quan sát thế giới. Nếu mẹ &amp;ldquo;cười&amp;rdquo; tức là mẹ đang &amp;ldquo;vui&amp;rdquo;. Khi &amp;ldquo;có nước trên mắt mẹ&amp;rdquo; thì chắc là mẹ &amp;ldquo;buồn&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Khái niệm cảm xúc bị ảnh hưởng bởi nền văn hóa và môi trường sống.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>My resolutions for 2022</title><link>https://japananh.github.io/p/my-resolutions-for-2022/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 23:45:12 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://japananh.github.io/p/my-resolutions-for-2022/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://japananh.github.io/p/my-resolutions-for-2022/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post My resolutions for 2022" />&lt;p>The coronavirus had changed the world and the way we live. I think 2021 was not a challenging year for me. I found it not too difficult to accomplish my career goals and my physical goals. Instead, working from home is pretty cool. I have more spare time to play with my buddies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One article of Fobes wrote that 2022 is going to be Malcolm Gladwell’s Tipping Point Year. This article pointed out 22 predictions of the world in 2022. It provides a lot of retrospective ideas for the new year. I highly recommend you read it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/michaelgale/2022/01/01/22-predictions-for-2022-and-why-this-is-malcolm-gladwells-tipping-point-year/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>https://www.forbes.com/sites/michaelgale/2022/01/01/22-predictions-for-2022-and-why-this-is-malcolm-gladwells-tipping-point-year/&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here are my resolutions for 2022&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Dive deep into backend development&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Dive deep into investing&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Finish reading list&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Challenge me physically &amp;amp; mentally&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Expand my network&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Moving into a new house&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Have fun + make fun of myself&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Try to be useful + help others&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add a bit of love to the world&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s go!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>IELTS Speaking Handbook - Chapter 2 - Understand the exam</title><link>https://japananh.github.io/p/ielts-speaking-handbook-chapter-2-understand-the-exam/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Dec 2021 04:06:20 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://japananh.github.io/p/ielts-speaking-handbook-chapter-2-understand-the-exam/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://japananh.github.io/p/ielts-speaking-handbook-chapter-2-understand-the-exam/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post IELTS Speaking Handbook - Chapter 2 - Understand the exam" />&lt;p>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/kientranhandbook" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Kiên Trần&lt;/a> là người có ảnh hướng lớn nhất tới lối tư duy học tiếng anh của tôi. Tôi nghĩ muốn giỏi tiếng anh hay bất kỳ lĩnh vực gì, đầu tiên, bạn phải vượt qua được trở ngại niềm tin, tức là bạn phải &lt;strong>THỰC SỰ TIN&lt;/strong> là mình có thể làm được.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Đọc sách Kiên sẽ giúp bạn &lt;strong>TẨY NÃO&lt;/strong>, khiến bạn tư duy tốt hơn và không còn phải HỌC tiếng anh một ngày nào. Sách không dùng các ví dụ khô khan như các giáo trình tiếng anh thông thường. Với hiểu biết phong phú về nhiều lĩnh vực khác nhau, mỗi cuốn sách của Kiên là một thế giới tràn đầy màu sắc, năng động, và thể hiện rõ tinh thần Bốn chấm không.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tôi đã đọc hết tất cả các sách của anh. Tuy nhiên, không phải nhận định nào của tác giả tôi cũng đồng tình, tôi sẽ chắt lọc ra những cái phù hợp với mình và bỏ qua toàn bộ cái còn lại.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Nào giờ thì chúng ta sẽ cùng nhau thưởng thức một phần chương 2 của cuốn sách số 8 - **IELTS Speaking Handbook - Understand the exam **&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="nội-dung-sách">Nội dung sách&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Thi Speaking sẽ gồm &lt;strong>3 phần&lt;/strong>. Phần 1 phần 2 và phần 3.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Section 1: Warm-up.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tại sao lại có section 1 cho warm up?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bởi làm gì có ai sẵn sàng ngay lập tức.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Trên đời này có 2 người lạ gặp nhau, bạn và giám khảo. Sẽ thật awkward cho cả
bạn và giám khảo nếu như bắt đầu test ngay lập tức.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Chính vì vậy người ta rất thông minh khi phát minh ra cái section 1 giúp cho bạn và
cả giám khảo bình tĩnh.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Ơ này, không phải chỉ có mỗi BẠN cần bình tĩnh, &lt;strong>GIÁM KHẢO cũng rất cần bình tĩnh&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Nhân tiện, nếu bạn đang đọc cuốn sách này của mình, khả năng cao bạn là một học sinh “ngoan” – theo nghĩa là overly nice/friendly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bạn biết không, đây là điều làm cho bạn có lợi thế hơn rất nhiều những người khác ở các vùng văn hoá khác. Họ quậy hơn và đôi khi còn annoying. Bạn nice và đó là một lợi thế giúp cho giám khảo bình tĩnh.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Hãy nhớ nhiệm vụ của bạn là &lt;strong>làm cho giám khảo bình tĩnh&lt;/strong>, thay vì
bạn mong giám khảo làm bạn bình tĩnh.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Vì bạn muốn bản thân bạn ở thế chủ động, bạn muốn bạn cầm đằng chuôi. Suy nghĩ trong đầu bạn không phải là &lt;em>“Liệu giám khảo có nice với mình không nhỉ?”&lt;/em>. Suy nghĩ trong đầu của bạn nên là &lt;em>“Mình phải làm gì để làm giám khảo bớt lo lắng và bình tĩnh hơn.”&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Hãy luôn luôn suy nghĩ như vậy trong suốt quá trình thi.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>“Hmm, ông ta có vẻ hơi run, chắc ông ta ngại mình”&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>“Làm thế nào để giám khảo bớt run?”&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>“Làm thế nào để giám khảo bình tĩnh hơn?”&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>“Mình sẽ phải nice và nói chậm lại để giám khảo bớt lo lắng.”&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Got it?&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="bình-luận-về-chương-2">Bình luận về chương 2&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Ai cũng biết bài thi IELTS Speaking đều có 3 phần. Điều khác biệt làm nên dấu ấn của tác giả ở chương 2 này là cách tư duy &lt;strong>làm cho giám khảo bình tĩnh&lt;/strong>. Một cú lừa bộ não thật khôn khéo rằng bạn đang là người nắm quyền ở đây. Bạn không phải đi thi nữa. Bạn đang ở nhà, chém gió với người ở &lt;em>cửa dưới&lt;/em> của bạn.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tôi đã đọc một cuốn sách mô tả rằng chúng ta có thể tự tưởng tượng ra những hình ảnh và tin rằng chúng là những sự kiện có thật.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Một người phụ nữ hồi tưởng lại quá khứ rằng mẹ cô ấy mất vì trượt chân xuống hồ bơi khi cô còn bé. Cô đã khẳng định với các nhà khoa học rằng những ký ức đấy hoàn toàn là sự thật. Nhưng rất lâu sau đó, khi tìm được những người chứng kiến cái chết của mẹ cô thì họ phát hiện là bà bị bệnh qua đời chứ không phải như những gì cô gái vẫn tin.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Con người có khả năng bóp méo ký ức và hoàn toàn tin tưởng điều này là sự thật. Tôi cũng hay dùng phương pháp này để khiến bản thân mình làm những điều đúng đắn nhiều hơn.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Ví dụ, tôi rất lười đọc textbook, vừa dài (cỡ trên 600 trang) và lại khó. Tôi tưởng tượng rằng mình rất quý tác giả, yêu tất cả những gì tác giả làm, ngắm hình tác giả, xem websites, nghĩ về cái bìa sách thật là ngầu&amp;hellip; Kiếm mọi lý do để thích cuốn sách này và vờ như mình rất đam mê nó.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Lúc đầu, tôi sẽ thấy hơi gượng nhưng sau khi đã luyện tập nó một thời dài thì tôi có thể làm việc này một cách tự động. Tôi đã đọc xong được 2 cuốn textbooks vào năm ngoái nhờ phương pháp này.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tôi nghĩ là việc đọc những cuốn trộn lẫn Anh-Việt kiểu này giúp ích cho tôi khá nhiều trong việc tư duy từ vựng. Đây là lối tư duy thông thường của đa số người học tiếng anh. Phải trải qua 2 bước thì thông tin mới tới não để xử lý.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;div class="chroma">
&lt;table class="lntable">&lt;tr>&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code>&lt;span class="lnt">1
&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>
&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-fallback" data-lang="fallback">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">Tiếng anh -&amp;gt; Tiếng việt -&amp;gt; Thông tin trong não
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>&lt;/tr>&lt;/table>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;p>Còn đây là cách bạn tư duy khi đọc sách của Kiên.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;div class="chroma">
&lt;table class="lntable">&lt;tr>&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code>&lt;span class="lnt">1
&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>
&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-fallback" data-lang="fallback">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">Tiếng anh -&amp;gt; Thông tin trong não
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>&lt;/tr>&lt;/table>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;p>Giả sử bạn đọc câu&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Sẽ thật &lt;strong>awkward&lt;/strong> cho cả bạn và giám khảo nếu như bắt đầu test ngay lập tức.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Ồ có một từ tiếng anh và nếu bạn không biết nghĩa của từ thì bạn hoàn toàn có thể đoán được là &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong>bất tiện&lt;/strong>&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;div class="chroma">
&lt;table class="lntable">&lt;tr>&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code>&lt;span class="lnt">1
&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>
&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-fallback" data-lang="fallback">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">awkward -&amp;gt; Cảm giác lúng túng, xấu hổ trong não
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>&lt;/tr>&lt;/table>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;p>Thay vì&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;div class="chroma">
&lt;table class="lntable">&lt;tr>&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code>&lt;span class="lnt">1
&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>
&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-fallback" data-lang="fallback">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">awkward -&amp;gt; Tra nghĩa tiếng việt -&amp;gt; Cảm giác lúng túng, xấu hổ trong não
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>&lt;/tr>&lt;/table>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Connect the dots</title><link>https://japananh.github.io/p/connect-the-dots/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Dec 2021 01:47:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://japananh.github.io/p/connect-the-dots/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://japananh.github.io/p/connect-the-dots/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Connect the dots" />&lt;p>I was a good student. I got high scores at school. I loved sciences, especially Mathematics. But I didn&amp;rsquo;t know what position I was supposed to do in the future.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My early 20s started by dropping out of university. I found it not for me. Students preferred certificates over knowledge. This wasn&amp;rsquo;t how to I used to think when I was 18. I was disappointed and upset.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To survive, I became a waitress, then a housekeeper, then a tailor. I live my career on autopilot.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Life is so boring. How to get out of it?&amp;rdquo; - I wondered.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In 2017, I made friends with some Uzbeks. They were computer science students at &lt;a class="link" href="https://inha.uz/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Inha University&lt;/a>. I was curious about what they do in their leisure time. So I asked them if they would like to share what they did. A week later, I wrote my first line of code in C++.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;div class="chroma">
&lt;table class="lntable">&lt;tr>&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code>&lt;span class="lnt">1
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">2
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">3
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">4
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">5
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">6
&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>
&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-fallback" data-lang="fallback">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">#include &amp;lt;iostream&amp;gt;
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">int main() {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> std::cout &amp;lt;&amp;lt; &amp;#34;Hello World!&amp;#34;;
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> return 0;
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">}
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>&lt;/tr>&lt;/table>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;p>I continued to learn to code for fun. It was hard. That&amp;rsquo;s why it was so fun.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Should I become a coder?&amp;rdquo; - I wondered.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>2 years later, I got my first job as a Web Developer. WOW! I did it without applying for an internship. I tripled my income. Awesome!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Last year, I experienced burnout and quit my job with no plan. Although this seemed terrible at first, I realized that not a bad decision. I started to acknowledge what I really want to become, what mistakes I made. I built some plans to expand my skillsets during this time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>4 months later, I got my second job.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Coming from a JavaScript background, I have always wanted to learn a static-typed programming language, this year I picked up &lt;strong>Go&lt;/strong> after reading the reviews about the language.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Now, 15 months in, I tried to fill the gap between me - an amateur and a professional. I&amp;rsquo;m happy with my career development. I do what I love every day - to build something useful.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you asked me what I was supposed to be in my early 20s. I would say I don&amp;rsquo;t know. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t good at anything and not interested in anything. Now, everything has changed.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>You can’t connect the dots looking forward; you can only connect them looking backward. – Steve Jobs&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></description></item><item><title>Accept Emotions As They Are</title><link>https://japananh.github.io/p/accept-emotions-as-they-are/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Dec 2021 00:29:55 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://japananh.github.io/p/accept-emotions-as-they-are/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://japananh.github.io/p/accept-emotions-as-they-are/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Accept Emotions As They Are" />&lt;p>I live in a country where most people think emotions should be ignored. Especially, negative emotions such as fear, anger, worry, loneliness, &amp;hellip; I had a very hard time trying to hide all my strong emotions and felt ashamed if someone saw them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Hey, you should be BRAVE. Don&amp;rsquo;t cry. Don&amp;rsquo;t let people see your stupid face.&amp;rdquo; - I told myself.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The strong emotion is something like a storm. if you try to hide your feelings, they might be accumulated into strong emotions. And you won&amp;rsquo;t develop a way to recognize your feelings correctly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For example, I misunderstood my &lt;strong>disappointment&lt;/strong> and my &lt;strong>sleep deprivation&lt;/strong> with an anxiety disorder. I thought something was wrong with my brain because none of my friends or coworkers behave like that. But in fact, I was just worried about my career path. That was fine for a younger.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>if you &lt;strong>acknowledge&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>transform&lt;/strong> your emotions instead of ignoring them, you won&amp;rsquo;t be afraid and won&amp;rsquo;t be overwhelmed by them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Of course, there are a lot of techniques to help you deal with emotions. Master Thich Nhat Hanh is one of the great people that help me to overcome my existential crisis and my burnout. He had a great &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bAbTMS-WEgM" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Dharma talk&lt;/a> about how to deal with strong or difficult emotions. &lt;a class="link" href="https://plumvillage.app/thich-nhat-hanh-on-how-to-deal-with-strong-emotions/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Here&lt;/a> is another great post from Plum Village. You can see that all practices are so simple, you can do it everywhere, every day. I hope it helps.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Handbook of thinking smart - Marginal Revenue vs Marginal Cost</title><link>https://japananh.github.io/p/handbook-of-thinking-smart-marginal-revenue-vs-marginal-cost/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Dec 2021 01:02:35 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://japananh.github.io/p/handbook-of-thinking-smart-marginal-revenue-vs-marginal-cost/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://japananh.github.io/p/handbook-of-thinking-smart-marginal-revenue-vs-marginal-cost/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Handbook of thinking smart - Marginal Revenue vs Marginal Cost" />&lt;p>I read &lt;strong>Handbook of thinking smart&lt;/strong>, the third book that was written by a Vietnamese author - &lt;strong>Kien Tran&lt;/strong>. I started to follow him in 2018. His first book - Handbook of IELTS motivated me to learn English from a zero to an intermediate. Although he received a bad reputation due to a fake IELTS certificate and other bad things, I still found a lot of useful advice in his books. Today, I&amp;rsquo;m gonna share the first chapter of this book with you.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="marginal-revenue-vs-marginal-cost-mr-vs-mc">Marginal Revenue vs Marginal Cost (MR vs MC)&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>You make decisions every day. Have you ever considered what you are doing is valuable or not?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this chapter, he introduces a famous concept in economics that you can apply immediately.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Always compare &lt;strong>Marginal Revenue&lt;/strong> (&lt;strong>MR&lt;/strong>) and &lt;strong>Marginal Cost&lt;/strong> (&lt;strong>MC&lt;/strong>).&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>MR is a benefit you get after you make a product.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>MC is a cost you pay after you make a product.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You hesitate to stay up an hour to do some IELTS reading exercises.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What is MR? It is a benefit you get after an hour of practicing IELTS.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What is MC? It is a cost you pay after an hour of practicing IETLS.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s 9 PM. If you stay up to 10 PM, you might finish 10 exercises. So 10 exercises are your MR.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Will you lose anything in that hour? Not much. You are not sleepy. You only lose an hour for doing something else. Therefore, MR &amp;gt; MC. You lose an hour to finish 10 exercises. You are happy and satisfied.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Example 2 is similar to the one above, but instead of 9 PM to 10 PM, it is 3 AM to 4 AM.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What is MR? It is a benefit you get after an hour of practicing IELTS. You&amp;rsquo;ll be sleepy, so you might not finish 10 exercises. Maybe 7. MR is 7 exercises.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What is MC? It is a cost you pay after an hour of practicing IETLS. You stay up very late, your cost is very high. You might wake up languidly the next morning and couldn&amp;rsquo;t focus on anything.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In that situation, you should NOT stay up late to practice IELTS because of MR &amp;lt; MC.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>MR and MC always exist in most situations. To make a better decision, you should determine them quickly.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Always compare MR with MC when making decisions on when.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></description></item><item><title>How to solve a coding interview question?</title><link>https://japananh.github.io/p/how-to-solve-a-coding-interview-question/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Dec 2021 01:28:50 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://japananh.github.io/p/how-to-solve-a-coding-interview-question/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://japananh.github.io/p/how-to-solve-a-coding-interview-question/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post How to solve a coding interview question?" />&lt;p>In this post, I&amp;rsquo;ll analyze an interview question. The purpose of these questions is to test candidates&amp;rsquo; technical knowledge, coding ability, problem-solving skills, and creativity. If you can&amp;rsquo;t find a complete solution, &lt;strong>it might be ok&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can find all code samples &lt;a class="link" href="https://replit.com/@japananh/dictionary" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="problem">Problem&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I was given an array of strings and a word. I need to create a function to test whether that word is in the array or not.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;div class="chroma">
&lt;table class="lntable">&lt;tr>&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code>&lt;span class="lnt">1
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">2
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">3
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">4
&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>
&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-text" data-lang="text">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">// input: [&amp;#34;car&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;cat&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;bar&amp;#34;]
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">isInDict(&amp;#34;car&amp;#34;) // true
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">isInDict(&amp;#34;cat&amp;#34;) // true
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">isInDict(&amp;#34;at&amp;#34;) // false
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>&lt;/tr>&lt;/table>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;h2 id="version-1">Version 1&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;code>Array.includes&lt;/code> in &lt;code>isInDict()&lt;/code> has a time complexity is O(n).&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;div class="chroma">
&lt;table class="lntable">&lt;tr>&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code>&lt;span class="lnt">1
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">2
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">3
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">4
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">5
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">6
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">7
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">8
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">9
&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>
&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-javascript" data-lang="javascript">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="kr">class&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nx">Dictionary&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nx">constructor&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">words&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="k">this&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">dict&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nx">words&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nx">isInDict&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">word&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="k">return&lt;/span> &lt;span class="k">this&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">dict&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">includes&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">word&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span> &lt;span class="c1">// O(n)
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="c1">&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>&lt;/tr>&lt;/table>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;div class="chroma">
&lt;table class="lntable">&lt;tr>&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code>&lt;span class="lnt">1
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">2
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">3
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">4
&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>
&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-javascript" data-lang="javascript">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="kr">const&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nx">dict&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="k">new&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nx">Dictionary&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">([&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;car&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;bar&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;cat&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;bat&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">])&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="nx">console&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">log&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">dict&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">isInDict&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;cat&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">))&lt;/span> &lt;span class="c1">// true
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="c1">&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">console&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">log&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">dict&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">isInDict&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;car&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">))&lt;/span> &lt;span class="c1">// true
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="c1">&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">console&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">log&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">dict&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">isInDict&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;ba&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">))&lt;/span> &lt;span class="c1">// false
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>&lt;/tr>&lt;/table>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;h2 id="version-2">Version 2&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I can improve the time complexity from &lt;code>O(n)&lt;/code> to &lt;strong>a constant time&lt;/strong> &lt;code>O(1)&lt;/code> by using &lt;code>Set.has()&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;div class="chroma">
&lt;table class="lntable">&lt;tr>&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code>&lt;span class="lnt">1
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">2
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">3
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">4
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">5
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">6
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">7
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">8
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">9
&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>
&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-javascript" data-lang="javascript">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="kr">class&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nx">Dictionary2&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nx">constructor&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">wordArr&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="k">this&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">dict&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="k">new&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nx">Set&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">wordArr&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nx">isInDict&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">word&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="k">return&lt;/span> &lt;span class="k">this&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">dict&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">has&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">word&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span> &lt;span class="c1">// O(1)
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="c1">&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>&lt;/tr>&lt;/table>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;div class="chroma">
&lt;table class="lntable">&lt;tr>&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code>&lt;span class="lnt">1
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">2
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">3
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">4
&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>
&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-javascript" data-lang="javascript">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="kr">const&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nx">dict&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="k">new&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nx">Dictionary&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">([&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;car&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;bar&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;cat&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;bat&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">])&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="nx">console&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">log&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">dict&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">isInDict&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;cat&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">))&lt;/span> &lt;span class="c1">// true
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="c1">&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">console&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">log&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">dict&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">isInDict&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;car&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">))&lt;/span> &lt;span class="c1">// true
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="c1">&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">console&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">log&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">dict&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">isInDict&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;ba&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">))&lt;/span> &lt;span class="c1">// false
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>&lt;/tr>&lt;/table>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;h2 id="version-3">Version 3&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>My code will fail if I pass a &lt;strong>regex&lt;/strong> into the &lt;code>isInDict&lt;/code> function.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;div class="chroma">
&lt;table class="lntable">&lt;tr>&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code>&lt;span class="lnt">1
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">2
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">3
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">4
&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>
&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-javascript" data-lang="javascript">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="kr">const&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nx">dict&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="k">new&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nx">Dictionary&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">([&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;car&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;bar&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;cat&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;bat&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">])&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="nx">console&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">log&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">dict&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">isInDict&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;cat&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">))&lt;/span> &lt;span class="c1">// true
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="c1">&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">console&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">log&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">dict&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">isInDict&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;ca*&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">))&lt;/span> &lt;span class="c1">// false -&amp;gt; incorrect
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="c1">&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">console&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">log&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">dict&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">isInDict&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;*at&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">))&lt;/span> &lt;span class="c1">// false -&amp;gt; incorrect
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>&lt;/tr>&lt;/table>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;p>To solve the problem, I create a new data structure. It might look like this.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;div class="chroma">
&lt;table class="lntable">&lt;tr>&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code>&lt;span class="lnt"> 1
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 2
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 3
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 4
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 5
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 6
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 7
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 8
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 9
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">10
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">11
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">12
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">13
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">14
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">15
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">16
&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>
&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-javascript" data-lang="javascript">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="nx">Dictionary&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nx">dict&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">:&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nx">car&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">:&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kc">true&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;*ar&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">:&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kc">true&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;c*r&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">:&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kc">true&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;ca*&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">:&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kc">true&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nx">bar&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">:&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kc">true&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;b*r&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">:&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kc">true&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;ba*&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">:&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kc">true&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nx">cat&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">:&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kc">true&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;*at&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">:&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kc">true&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;c*t&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">:&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kc">true&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nx">bat&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">:&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kc">true&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;b*t&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">:&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kc">true&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>&lt;/tr>&lt;/table>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;p>After refactoring the &lt;code>constructor()&lt;/code>, the final code will look like this.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;div class="chroma">
&lt;table class="lntable">&lt;tr>&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code>&lt;span class="lnt"> 1
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 2
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 3
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 4
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 5
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 6
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 7
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 8
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt"> 9
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">10
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">11
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">12
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">13
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">14
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">15
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">16
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">17
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">18
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">19
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">20
&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>
&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-javascript" data-lang="javascript">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="kr">class&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nx">Dictionary&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nx">constructor&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">words&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="k">this&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">dict&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nx">words&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">reduce&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">((&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">acc&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nx">word&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">=&amp;gt;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nx">acc&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">[&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">word&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">]&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kc">true&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nx">word&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">split&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">).&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">forEach&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">((&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">letter&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nx">i&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">=&amp;gt;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="kr">const&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nx">start&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nx">word&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">slice&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="mi">0&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nx">i&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="kr">const&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nx">end&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nx">word&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">slice&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">i&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">+&lt;/span> &lt;span class="mi">1&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="kr">const&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nx">partialWord&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="sb">`&lt;/span>&lt;span class="si">${&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">start&lt;/span>&lt;span class="si">}&lt;/span>&lt;span class="sb">*&lt;/span>&lt;span class="si">${&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">end&lt;/span>&lt;span class="si">}&lt;/span>&lt;span class="sb">`&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nx">acc&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">[&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">partialWord&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">]&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kc">true&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">})&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="k">return&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nx">acc&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">},&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{})&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nx">isInDict&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">word&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="k">return&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">!!&lt;/span>&lt;span class="k">this&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">dict&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">[&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">word&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">]&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>&lt;/tr>&lt;/table>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;div class="chroma">
&lt;table class="lntable">&lt;tr>&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code>&lt;span class="lnt">1
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">2
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">3
&lt;/span>&lt;span class="lnt">4
&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>
&lt;td class="lntd">
&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-javascript" data-lang="javascript">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="kr">const&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nx">dict&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="k">new&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nx">Dictionary&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">([&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;car&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;bar&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;cat&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;bat&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">])&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="nx">console&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">log&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">dict&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">isInDict&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;cat&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">))&lt;/span> &lt;span class="c1">// true
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="c1">&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">console&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">log&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">dict&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">isInDict&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;ca*&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">))&lt;/span> &lt;span class="c1">// true
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="c1">&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">console&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">log&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">dict&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">isInDict&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;*at&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">))&lt;/span> &lt;span class="c1">// true
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/td>&lt;/tr>&lt;/table>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div></description></item></channel></rss>