<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>neuroscience on The Writer At Heart</title><link>https://japananh.github.io/tags/neuroscience/</link><description>Recent content in neuroscience on The Writer At Heart</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2022 00:38:47 +0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://japananh.github.io/tags/neuroscience/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Autumn Notes - A Reconsideration of The Real Life</title><link>https://japananh.github.io/p/autumn-notes-a-reconsideration-of-real-life/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2022 00:38:47 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://japananh.github.io/p/autumn-notes-a-reconsideration-of-real-life/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://japananh.github.io/p/autumn-notes-a-reconsideration-of-real-life/cover.jpeg" alt="Featured image of post Autumn Notes - A Reconsideration of The Real Life" />&lt;p>&lt;strong>Autumn Notes&lt;/strong> is the last note of the series 100 Days of Challenge that I wrote in the Autumn of 2022. This is a random-thought post as usual. The content is about what I learned, how I overcome my difficulties, and why things work.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="dopamine">Dopamine&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Loss of motivation is the most difficult thing that I need to deal with in the recent year. Working on others’ projects, fixing bugs, following others’ rules, and sometimes dealing with toxic work culture drove me crazy and exhausted. I found myself lost and overwhelmed by almost everything.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At that time, my English got better and I started to listen to &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.youtube.com/c/AndrewHubermanLab" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>The Huberman Lab&lt;/a> at their very first episodes. The &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=p3JLaF_4Tz8" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>conversation&lt;/a> between Prof. Huberman (the host) and Dr. Anna Lembke (the guest) about Dopamine enlighten me about why and how all these things happened. I didn&amp;rsquo;t notice that my dopamine level was very low at that time so I have no mood on anything.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Dopamine&lt;/strong> is &lt;strong>a feel-good neurotransmitter&lt;/strong> that plays a role in many functions in the body, including motivation, mood, attention, and memory. If your dopamine level is very low, you might have almost no motivation to do anything.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A &lt;strong>neurotransmitter&lt;/strong> is a chemical messenger that transmits signals in the body. It also acts as a hormone.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>To learn more about Dopamine and how it works to control your mood, I recommend you read the amazing and detailed Dopamine paper: &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4826767/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4826767/&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After a year of trial and error, here are 3 things that significant improve my mood:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Viewing sunlight in the morning (before 8 AM) and/or in the late afternoon (after 4 PM).&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>I think the lack of vitamin D (D3) is due to covering my body by wearing like a ninja outside and working indoors all day. In the summer, it seemed reasonable when I protected my body this way. But in the winter, the lack of sunlight decreased my performance at work. I felt tired and low mood all day.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>No one ever told me about the relationship between sunlight (especially blue light) and the alert system in the human brain. Sunlight suspends melatonin in the human brain. Melatonin is a hormone that your brain produces in response to darkness. That way if we feel alert when we view the sunlight.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For more information, I hightly recommend you watch this episode from The Huberman Lab: &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UF0nqolsNZc" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UF0nqolsNZc&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol start="2">
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Magnesium&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Magnesium plays many crucial roles in the body, such as supporting muscle and nerve function and energy production. Huberman mentioned &lt;strong>Magnesium&lt;/strong> as a great supplement for sleep, mood, and exercising in one episode (sorry, I forgot its name). You can read more studies about the benefits of Magnesium in &lt;a class="link" href="https://examine.com/summaries/?filter=supplements&amp;amp;value=magnesium" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Examine&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I started to use Magnesium supplements 5 months ago. My dose is &lt;strong>400 mg a day&lt;/strong> (an average dose for women my age), &lt;strong>before bed&lt;/strong>. You can use it after your workout session or before bed depending on the way you feel better. I was dealing with sleep quality so I used it before bed. If your priority is improving training, you can use it after training.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol start="3">
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Sleep control&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>I tracked my sleep quality with a smart band that connected to my phone via Bluetooth. The app analyzed my sleep via some indicators such as the time woke up, the time to bed, regularity of rising time, deep sleep continuity, etc. When all indicators are normal, it means high sleep quality. Trying to improve as many indicators as I can help me feel relaxed and calm the next day.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-rules-of-thirds">The rules of thirds&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I started my powerlifting journey and prepared for my first meet 4 months ago. This sport is not easy for me, an absolute beginner. I was struggling with SBD techniques for the first 2 months (didn&amp;rsquo;t know how to hold the bar and arching in bench, good-morning squat, conven-sumo deadlift, etc). I cried, yelled at myself and thought of quitting it. The rules of thirds by &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.instagram.com/alexipappas" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Alexi Pappas&lt;/a>, came into my life as a magic Mantra.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I couldn&amp;rsquo;t hit my last exercise 2 weeks ago. Then it happened again a week later. 2 weeks left before the meet. I was crying so hard. I didn&amp;rsquo;t know why. My mood was down. Then I thought of the rules of thirds and counted my sessions. 2 crappy days (3.3%) along the 4 months (60 sessions). The ratio is quite good. Well, the number never lies you. No cry, no anxiety.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;When you are chasing a dream or doing anything hard, you&amp;rsquo;ve meant to feel &lt;strong>GOOD&lt;/strong> a third of the time, &lt;strong>OKAY&lt;/strong> a third of the time, and &lt;strong>CRAPPY&lt;/strong> a third of the time. If the ratio roughly in that range, then you&amp;rsquo;re doing fine. Today was a crappy day, along your dream chasing.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Note: Alexi Pappas is a Greek-American runner, filmmaker, actor, and writer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Reference: &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.instagram.com/tv/CgF3hJWlqdM" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>https://www.instagram.com/tv/CgF3hJWlqdM&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sleepiness">Sleepiness&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Beside the loss of motivation, I also deal with the sleepiness in the morning that affected my performance at work.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>First, I started with nutrition as the easiest way to manipulate my sleep. I used to be a high-carbs eater (&amp;gt;= 60%) for a long time. It turned out &lt;strong>reducing carbs down to 50%&lt;/strong> helps reduce sleepiness because my stomach doesn’t need to spend a lot of energy to digest carbs and the insulin level won’t peak too high.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Intermittent fasting&lt;/strong> also works well for me, I skip breakfast on the day I do work out in the morning due to no time to cook in the morning. I maintained macros, just no breakfast. After 3 months, I saw some amazing results such as:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>My body recomposition improved, my abs decreased from 71 to 68 cm.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I look leaner and don’t be annoyed because of my full stomach. I started to realize that I love an empty stomach in the morning.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>No sleepiness in the morning and afternoon, except my sleeping period, is too short (below 5 hours) or the sleeping quality is not good.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>As a result, the incredible thing happened that I started to feel hungry at meal time (3 times a day in the morning/noon/night) after a year of no hungry at all. Therefore, I stopped intermittent fasting and my eating routine back to normal. Life always compensate us in some way if we work hard.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Second, I still fall asleep more quickly on rainy/cloudy days. The greatest way to find a solution of any problem is figuring out why it happened. Here are some reasons that cause sleepiness on rainy/cloudy days.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The increased negative ion content in the air.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Rainy sounds are lullabies.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Studies have found that when rain sounds enter people’s brains, the brain unconsciously relaxes and produces alpha waves, which are very close to the state of the brain when a human sleeps.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Increased secretion of melatonin in the body when it darks
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.sleepfoundation.org/melatonin" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Darkness prompts the pineal gland to start producing melatonin while light causes that production to stop.&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Decreased oxygen content in the air.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Oxygen can stimulate the brain and make us feel refreshed. When it rains, there is more water vapor in the air, which results in lower air pressure and a relative decrease in oxygen content. In such a situation, the brain begins to slack off, and people will feel sleepy.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>When understood the causes, I didn&amp;rsquo;t found myself lost in negative thoughts that ruined my days. I came up with some solutions.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Make the room as bright as possible (Light suspends the melatonin).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Take a deep breath (To increase the oxygen content in my body).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Increase heart rate by exercising or talking to someone (Increases my dopamine level and alert my brain).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="compassion">Compassion&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="link" href="https://lexfridman.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Lex Fridman&lt;/a>, the famous AI researcher, is the first guy to teach me about &lt;strong>compassion&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>love&lt;/strong> on his podcast, but Q is the guy who motivated me to make my first move. I&amp;rsquo;m quite good at Maths and logic but very bad at learning abstract things and emotions. Compassion requires deep observation, mindfulness, and patience.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Self-help books taught me to spend most of my time with great people.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;We are the average of the five people we spend the most time with.&amp;rdquo; - &lt;a class="link" href="jimrohn.com" >Jim Rohn&lt;/a> said.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Great&amp;rdquo; means wealthy, flourishing career, good-looking, blissful relationship, etc. If you don&amp;rsquo;t fall under the criteria, I will ignore you. That mindset caused me a ton of trouble in daily life. I compared myself to others and developed low self-esteem. I also treated people unfairly by their &amp;ldquo;success status&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>How do I know where I am in my success status when I don&amp;rsquo;t compare myself to others?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When I thought I&amp;rsquo;m on a higher level, I ignored the existence of the &amp;ldquo;lower&amp;rdquo; people. On the other side, I felt &amp;ldquo;motivated&amp;rdquo; to move forward when I see success people. But that motivation was just an illusion. It took me weeks, months, or even years to accomplish my goals. Meanwhile, most time I felt jealous and ashamed by the thought I was not good enough, or people might call it &lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;Imposter syndrome&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When Q told me about the class hierarchy of wealthy people vs poor people, we debated for an hour and I suspected most of his arguments and reasoning. We didn&amp;rsquo;t discuss more about this topic after that. A few weeks later, I saw a comic named &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.facebook.com/thewokesalaryman/posts/pfbid02MoANmdVSANzPG3TGmmEapui67LQAtpTXMixzD3DWWWZk8FaoT9rqpLZNQFK6KAZTl" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Hedonic treadmill&lt;/a> about the way we live our lives by breaking old boxes and fall into more comfortable boxes, do it again until we are satisfied with our lives. I found my Aha! moment.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When I was in a fresher position, I thought of my career path and saw my coworkers and my friends working so hard to get their dream jobs. They double/triple their salary in the next 2 years and became superman at work. When I compared myself to them, I was distressed. I didn&amp;rsquo;t realize that they have NO personal life. They work all day and hang out with family or friends at weekends or holidays. They don&amp;rsquo;t exercise and don&amp;rsquo;t have a &amp;ldquo;balance work-life&amp;rdquo;. Their body shapes and their health become worse. Some of them fall into the mindset of cold-hearted as I did. I respect their hard-working, and they contribute value to the world but I quite dislike the way they live.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The way I disliked my family is they were born in a box and lived their whole life in that box. No ambition, no improvement. I blamed them for laziness and backwardness. I felt ashamed of my behaviors. They have their choices. They are satisfied with their boxes. So do I.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This is the last note of the series &lt;a class="link" href="http://thewriteratheart.com/categories/100-days-of-challenge/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>&lt;strong>100 Days of Challenge&lt;/strong>&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I started this series just want to write down what I observed in my daily life with the philosophy is &lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;Doing it for fun&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>. A year look back, I have a blog with 100 posts and some new friends came into my life unexpectedly. I realize that I love &lt;strong>reading&lt;/strong>, &lt;strong>writing&lt;/strong>, and &lt;strong>sharing&lt;/strong>. The more I write, the more I understand myself and become a better me. Smart brain with a compassionate heart.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Welcome to my world!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Ghi Chép Ngắn Về Huberman Lab Podcast Số 88</title><link>https://japananh.github.io/p/ghi-chep-ngan-ve-huberman-lab-podcast-so-88/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2022 09:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://japananh.github.io/p/ghi-chep-ngan-ve-huberman-lab-podcast-so-88/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://japananh.github.io/p/ghi-chep-ngan-ve-huberman-lab-podcast-so-88/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Ghi Chép Ngắn Về Huberman Lab Podcast Số 88" />&lt;p>Lần đầu tiên, tôi nghe trọn vẹn một podcast trong lúc nấu ăn và não không bị lạc đi một phương trời xa xôi nào đấy. Phải nói là có nhiều tools hay và tính áp dụng cao. Tôi thực sự phục bác Huberman vì sự đơn giản trong cách giải thích về cơ chế hoạt động của các chất dẫn truyền thần kinh và các tools áp dụng.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dưới đây là ghi chép ngắn của tôi về những thứ tôi thấy thú vị ở &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yb5zpo5WDG4" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Podcast số 88 - Optimize your focus&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="nghiên-cứu-ở-phòng-thí-nghiệm-của-giáo-sư-thần-kinh-học-wendy-suzuki">Nghiên cứu ở phòng thí nghiệm của Giáo sư thần kinh học Wendy Suzuki&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>15 phút thiền trong vòng 30 ngày liên tục cải thiện tập trung và trí nhớ. Bạn có thể xem thêm Giáo sư Wendy Suzuki giải thích lợi ích của thiền ở &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uYaUVNxL_fo" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>đây&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Cá nhân tôi từng vượt qua giai đoạn burnout, phải nghỉ việc trong nhiều tháng liền vì không có một chút hào hứng với cuộc sống xung quanh. Ngồi thiền hàng ngày, nghe bài giảng pháp suốt 6 tháng trời giúp tôi vượt qua nên tôi thấy trải nghiệm này hoàn toàn đáng thử nếu bạn thấy mình khó tập trung.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="nhịn-ăn-gián-đoạn-giúp-tập-trung-và-tăng-năng-suất-khi-làm-việc">Nhịn ăn gián đoạn giúp tập trung và tăng năng suất khi làm việc.&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Tôi đã trải nghiệm nhịn ăn gián đoạn từ tháng 7, tính tới hiện tại là hơn 3 tháng. Sau 1 năm ép bản thân ăn để tăng cân thì đây là quãng thời gian bụng tôi cảm thấy nhẹ nhàng như kỳ nghỉ. Tôi không ngờ là làm việc với cái bụng &amp;ldquo;rỗng&amp;rdquo; khiến tôi tập trung hơn và không còn cảm giác buồn ngủ hay đầy bụng như hồi tôi cố ép bản thân &amp;ldquo;ăn sáng&amp;rdquo; cho đủ chỉ tiêu.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Sliding window của tôi bắt đầu từ lúc 8:30 giờ tối hôm trước (khi kết thúc bữa ăn) cho tới 12 giờ sáng hôm sau. Nghĩa là tổng calories và macro không đổi, tôi bỏ bữa sáng, chỉ ăn bữa trưa và tối. Nếu thấy đói nhẹ vào buổi sáng sau khi tỉnh dậy thì tôi sẽ ăn nhẹ với 1 quả trứng/1 lát bánh mỳ/1 chiếc energy bar. Nhưng thú vị là cả tháng tôi chỉ thấy đói chưa tới 5 lần.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Nếu các bạn dễ tăng cân buồn phiền về cân nặng của mình thì một đứa skinny như tôi cũng ám ảnh không kém về cân nặng của mình. Tôi ép mình ăn tới mức hầu như không thấy đói bụng ở bất kỳ thời điểm nào trong ngày. Mọi sự tính toán, cộng trừ, điều chỉnh, cheat để tăng calories đều chỉ làm tôi tăng lên 1-2 kg trong ngắn hạn (1-3 tháng). Chỉ cần một hôm ốm hay quá stress là tôi lại sụt cân. Bao nhiêu nỗ lực tan hết. Một người bạn nói với tôi rằng có thể cơ thể tôi &amp;ldquo;thích&amp;rdquo; cân nặng đấy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Sau vài tuần ngắm mình trong gương và nhìn cơ thể mình từ những video ghi lại quá trình training thì tôi lại thấy thích cái thân hình hiện tại. Tôi nhớ là hồi 2017 tôi đã tập bụng và cardio rất nhiều, mơ một ngày nào đó có cái bụng phẳng lì, tách đôi như hiện tại. Mà giờ tôi còn chả thèm tập bụng cơ. Bạn sẽ thấy nhiều điều bất ngờ lắm khi bạn quan sát bản thân bằng cặp mắt của một người ngoài nhìn vào. Well, có thể anh bạn tôi đã đúng. Tôi bắt đầu hài lòng với cơ thể mình. May quá, không phải ép ăn nữa.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="tác-động-tích-cực-của-ánh-nắng-mặt-trời-trong-đó-có-ánh-sáng-xanh-bluelight-đối-với-hệ-thần-kinh">Tác động tích cực của ánh nắng mặt trời, trong đó có ánh sáng xanh (bluelight) đối với hệ thần kinh.&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Lợi ích lớn nhất của ánh nắng mặt trời tôi cảm nhận được đó là tình trạng mood của bản thân. Tôi không tài nào giải thích được lý do cả mùa đông năm ngoái tôi đã trì trệ và uể oải dù có chăm chỉ tập, ăn uống và ngủ đúng giờ cho tới khi phát hiện ra lợi ích của ánh sáng mặt trời vào ban ngày thông qua Huberman Lab.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Nỗi ám ảnh về ung thư da và sự truyền thông sai lệch khiến đa số phụ nữ (trong đó có cả tôi), tin sái cổ vào việc chúng ta cần phải bịt kín mít như ninja để bảo vệ làn da khỏi &amp;ldquo;tác hại&amp;rdquo; của ánh sáng mặt trời. Phải cho tới khi sự uể oải của bản thân giảm nhờ chăm chỉ phơi nắng sáng sớm (trước 8 giờ sáng) và chiều tối sau 4 giờ chiều thì tôi mới thực sự tin vào ích lợi của ánh nắng mặt trời và vai trò của vitamin D tới hệ thần kinh.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Vitamin D có hai dạng chính là D3 (đây là dạng cơ thể sản sinh dưới ánh sáng mặt trời) và D2 (thực vật sản sinh do tác động của ánh sáng mặt trời). Nên dùng D3 vì đây là dạng cơ thể sản sinh ra, tránh D2 vì cơ thể phải chuyển hoá chúng nên tỷ lệ hấp thụ không cao. Phơi nắng tối thiểu 30 phút mỗi ngày vào sáng sớm (trước 8 giờ) và chiều tối (sau 4 giờ) là lời khuyên cực kỳ hợp lý. Hôm nào, trời âm u thì cứ thấy nắng lúc nào là tôi lao ra phơi bất chấp.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bên cạnh đó, những lời khuyên khác cũng cải thiện việc đau đầu và mỏi mắt của tôi khi phải dùng máy tính thường xuyên (9 - 10 tiếng/ngày) đó là &amp;ldquo;Let the bluelight into your eyes in the early morning or late in the afternoon&amp;rdquo; (để mắt tiếp xúc với ánh sáng mặt trời). Và khi nghỉ ngơi, cố gắng tập trung nhìn ra một điểm rất xa (có thể là nhìn lên trời hay nhìn sang một toà nhà cách mình vài trăm mét).&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="chế-độ-ăn-keto-keep-eating-the-fat-off">Chế độ ăn Keto (Keep Eating The fat Off)&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Keto là viết tắt của Keep Eating The fat Off, là chế độ ăn hạn chế tinh bột (carbs), giữ protein vùa phải và tăng cường nhiều chất béo. Nhiều nhà khoa học tôi theo dõi từng nói về lợi ích của Keto, trong đó có cả Lex Fridman và Andrew Huberman. Tôi chưa có trải nghiệm nào với Keto nhưng tôi đã từng trải nghiệm chế độ Low-carb (khá giống Keto ở việc hạn chế tinh bột, chỉ khác tỷ lệ chất béo và protein) trong 1 năm.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tôi cắt tinh bột xuống còn 1 bát cơm/ngày (~ 60 - 70 gram gạo trắng). Cơ thể tôi nổi mụn liên tục từ mặt, lưng, ngực, tay, chân. Tình trạng này hoàn toàn chấm dứt khi tôi chuyển sang vegan. Tôi kể ra câu chuyện này chỉ muốn nói rằng chế độ ăn phụ thuộc rất nhiều vào bộ gen và thói quen sinh hoạt của bạn. Nếu nghiên cứu bảo tốt hoặc &amp;ldquo;đa số&amp;rdquo; bảo tốt mà bạn trải nghiệm một thời gian không thấy hiệu quả như vậy. Thì nên thử cách khác.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="non-sleep-deep-rest-nsdr">Non Sleep Deep Rest (NSDR)&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>NSDR là một thuật ngữ được bác Huberman nhắc tới trong nhiều tập podcast khác nhau. Lợi ích của NSDR là giúp cơ thể thư giãn, cải thiện giấc ngủ. Trong tập này, bác Huberman có giới thiệu cách áp dụng NSDR giúp bạn tỉnh táo hơn khi ở trong trạng thái thiếu ngủ mà cần tập trung làm việc. Tôi mới bắt đầu tìm hiểu NSDR vào tháng này và sẽ viết một bài review về trải nghiệm của bản thân.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="thực-phẩm-bổ-sung-supplements">Thực phẩm bổ sung (Supplements)&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Tôi rất đồng tình với bác Huberman rằng chúng ta nên tập trung vào tools đầu tiên rồi mới tới thực phẩm bổ sung và cuối cùng là đi tham vấn người có chuyên môn hơn (bác sỹ, nhà tâm lý học, &amp;hellip;). Thực phẩm bổ sung là thứ hỗ trợ, chúng không phải là thần dược. Tất cả thực phẩm bổ sung và liều dùng được khuyến nghị trong podcast này đều tập trung vào cải thiện khả năng tập trung.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Cái tên được nêu đầu bảng là Omega 3, cụ thể là EPA omega 3, dùng với liều lượng 1 - 3 gram/ngày giúp cải thiện khả năng nhận thức. Nếu bạn không chắc chắn mình ăn đủ cá giàu Omega 3 thì nên dùng thực phẩm bổ sung.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bên cạnh lợi ích gịúp tăng sự phát triển cơ bắp (dạng Creatine phosphate), Creatine còn có tác dụng cải thiện chức năng thần kinh. Bác Huberman gợi ý 5 gram/ngày (dạng Creatine monohydrate), dạng bột pha với nước uống.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="kết-luận">Kết luận&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Còn nhiều thứ thú vị được nghe mà tôi chưa nhớ ra được khi ngồi viết bài này. Bác Huberman có để timeline của podcast trong phần description, rất tiện để tra cứu nội dung. Hi vọng những kiến thức khoa học sẽ ngày càng được phổ biến hơn ở Việt Nam.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>